اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Chapter Nine: On Dueling,
translating Mubariza(مُبَارزَة), as dueling,
which is pretty much the closest translation you can get for the word Mubariza(مُبَارزَة),
the way it(Dueling) used to happen in the old days is that, this(Dueling) is before the actual battle starts.
Someone who is well known with a reputation of being good fighter,
he would come ahead before the battle starts, while the armies are still meeting,
and would ask for a challenge for one man to come out and challenge him.
This is sort of like the ceremony to open the celebration of the actual battle.
And we know what happened in the Battle of Badr(بدر), in fact Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) does talk about that,
where three of the Mushrikeen(مشركين) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
Ut'ba Bin Rabiyah(عُتْبَة بن ربيعة), Shaibah(شيبة) and Al-Walid Bin Ut'ba(ألوليدبن عُتْبَة) three of them set out for Mubariza(مُبَارزَة).
And this also existed even in the era of firearms.
Where, you had the duels in the wild, wild west,
where people will do those 10 steps and then you turn around and shoot your opponent,
stuff that is not only in the movies, it's absolutely bad that happened.
One of the US presidents was or president candidate was killed in a duel.
So Mubariza(مُبَارزَة) is something that carried on until quite recently.
Dueling is allowed according to the consensus of the scholars,
accepting the invitation to duel by an non-believers is recommended.
Asking for a duel is neither recommended nor discouraged, according to the Maz'hab(مذهب) of As-Shafie(ألشَّافعي),
it is appropriate for the experienced, and is discouraged for the weak, doesn't have sufficient confidence in himself.
You don't went to go out, bravado and just ask for duel, when you don't have the ability to stand up to the opponent.
Why? Because that demoralizes the army.
The Mubariza(مُبَارزَة) that happened before the Battle of Badr(بدر),
played a very important role in demoralizing the army of the disbelievers
because all of their three men who came up with Mubariza(مُبَارزَة) were killed.
So it is Makroh(مكروع) for the one, who is not capable.
In fact, it is said that it is prohibited for such a person to ask for duel,
it is Sunnah(سنة) get the permission of the Ameer(أمير), but it is still allowed without his knowledge,
because duels don't only happen before the battle, but within the battle you could call on somebody, you see, for a duel.
Imam Malik(امام مالك) was asked about the ones, who stand out in front of the army and asked for a duel,
he said:
It depends on his intentions, if he's doing it for the sake of Allah, I do not see a problem with that,
since that was the tradition of the ones before us.
Imam As-Shafie(إمام ألشَّافعي) said: I don't see a problem with duels.
Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) says: Know that duels during wars and accepting the invitation to it is the way of the heroes.
It is a badge of honor for the brave men and it has been their pride, after Islam and before it.
Amr Bin Abd Wud(عمروبن عبدود), one of the greatest fighters of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
During the Battle of Al-Khandaq(ألخندق), the trench came out asking for a duel.
Amr Bin Abd Wud(عمروبن عبدود) was quite a formidable opponent.
He was an old man at that time.
I think it's a bit of an exaggeration but some say that he was over 80 years of age or something.
But sometimes, you know, not all of these, details, tend to be authentic.
Anyway, he was famous as being a very brave man and a very strong fighter.
So he comes out and he asks for duel.
So, Ali(علي) veiled in iron armory stood up and said: I would!
Rasool Allah ﷺ refused to allow him and said:
إنَّه عمرو
This is Amr(عمرو).
Sit down!
So Amr Bin Abd Wud(عمروبن عبدود) called again,
Isn't there a man among you, where's your paradise that you claim whoever dies among you will enter it?
He is mocking now.
Isn't there a man among you, who can stand up and face me.
You claim that Jannah(جنة) is...
come ahead and I'll send you in Jannah(جنة).
So, it was Ali(علي) who stood up again and said: I would!
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him,
إنَّه عمرو
Sit down! This is Amr(عمر)!
You're too young for that.
Now Amr(عمرو) calls again for a third time and he's reciting some lines of poetry, challenging the Muslims
so Ali(علي) stood for the third time and said: I would!
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: It is Amr(عمرو), Ali(علي) responded,
وان كان عمر
And what if it is Amr(عمرو).?
So what!
So Rasool Allah ﷺ this time allowed them after refusing three times.
So Amr(عمرو) told him: Who are you?
Now, he cannot see the face of Ali(علي), because Ali(علي) is covered in Chain male,
and so was Amr Bin Abd Wud(عمروبن عبدود),
so he wants to know who's this man who was coming forth.
So he said who are you?
He said: I am Ali(علي), the son of Abu Talib(ابوطالب).
Amr(عمرو) said: Have someone senior to you step forward instead,
I wouldn't want to spell your blood, my son.
So he is having mercy on this young man, he said: Son, I don't want to kill you.
Send someone else who's senior to you.
Ali(علي) didn't responded by saying, but I would be very happy to spell yours.
So Amr(عمرو) was quite furious with that statement.
So he walked towards Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), and he pulled out his sword violently from his Sheath,
as if it was a blaze of fire that's how it was described when Amr(عمرو) pulled out his sword.
It was as if he was pulling out the blaze of fire,
he pulled it out, very violently.
And the battle started between the two.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want to look at it,
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want to even watch.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was not watching what was happening,
Rasool Allah ﷺ was concerned for his, relative Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب).
So he wasn't watching.
So these two men are fighting and the Muslims are surrounding and watching what's happening.
And you have now a cloud of dust is erupting.
And it was quite a violent fight, you just barely see them, in this cloud of dust.
So Amr Bin Abd Wud(عمروبن عبدود), he struck, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب),
but Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) protect himself with his shield.
So the sword of Amr Bin Abd Wud(عمروبن عبدود) got stuck in the shield of Ali(علي),
and that's when Ali(علي) hit him, and killed him, and the Muslims made Takbir(تكبير).
And that's when Rasool Allah ﷺ knew the results of the fight,
the Messenger of Allah, then heard the thunderous Takbir(تكبير) of the Muslims,
and this is mentioned by Ibn-e-Hisham(إبن هشام),
while Khalid(خالد) was laying siege to a town, one of their fighters came out of the gates with a sword in his right hand,
and a shield in his left, and he asked for a duel.
By the way, this thought just came up to my mind.
You know, usually, because most people are right handed so you would carry the sword with the right hand
and the shield with your left,
now there's this Muslim fortress in Tarifa(طريفة), Spain.
And I just happened to visit a few weeks ago.
And by the way this is a port city it's now more of a tourist town
and most of the tourists come from this country they just go there to party, it's a Mediterranean resort.
It's called Tarifa(طريفة), and it's named after the first Muslims clan there.
Now contrary to common understanding that Tariq Bin Ziad(طارق بن زياد) is the first one, to get into Spain, he actually wasn't.
Tariq Bin Ziad(طارق بن زياد) was the second army to go to Spain.
The first was a reconnaissance army led by Tareef(طريف),
by Imam Bin Tareef(إمام بن طريف), he is from Al-Berber(ألبربر).
And he was sent by Musa Bin Nusair(موسى بن نصير) to go into Spain.
The way this whole thing happened is,
you know the Muslims were not thinking about the crossing into Europe.
Musa Bin Nusair(موسى بن نصير), and the Muslim armies were going through Africa
and they didn't have on mind crossing to the European continent,
you know, in those days you don't have any maps you don't have any satellite images, so it's an unknown land, to them.
They never been there, they don't have any reports coming to them, so they have no idea what's behind the sea,
they could see it, you could see, Spain from Morocco,
but you need to know what's going on there.
So what happened was that,
there was one fortress on the African coast, only one fortress that was still under Roman command.
The General who was leading that fortress, his name is Julian,
the tradition was that they would send their children to the Spanish court to be educated.
And the king of Spain at that time was in the Arabic literature he's named Radreeq(رزريق),
but the Spanish name is Rodriguez.
So they would send their children to be educated in the Spanish court.
So Julian he sent his daughter to Spain.
Now, apparently she was attractive so Rodriguez attacked her.
When Julian knew about that, he went to the Muslims, and asked them to help him and invade Spain.
So, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), you see
how this dispute that happened among them was the reason that brought the Muslims into Spain,
to start up this huge Islamic civilization for eight centuries in the Iberian Peninsula.
So Julian went to Musa Bin Nusair(موسى بن نصير) and he said: I can lead you into Spain.
Now, Musa Bin Nusair(موسى بن نصير) was a very cautious leader.
He felt that this might be a plot by the Christians to drag in the Muslims and the defeat them.
So he said: To prove, that you're honest, I want you to go in and you fight against Rodriguez.
So, that I can know that now you cut your ties with him.
Julian did go in and he fought inside Spain and then he came out he said: Now send an army.
Musa Bin Nusair(موسى بن نصير) were still reluctant so what he did,
he sent a small army of 700, led by Tareef(طريف) to go into Spain.
So these were the first Muslims sent into Spain, they went they landed in this port city of Tareef(طريف).
They raided the area around them they took some Ghanaem(غنائم), and they came back.
So now he has a report, in addition to the Ghanaem(غنائم), to give to Musa Bin Nusair(موسى بن نصير).
Musa Bin Nusair(موسى بن نصير) still does not want to risk going by himself,
so he sends Tariq Bin Ziad(طارق بن زياد) in an army of 7000.
And that's when the Fath(فتح), starts.
Anyway, the reason why I'm mentioning this, the castle Tarif(طريف) that the Muslims built.
In case the lines of defense are broken and some enemy soldiers are able to get into the castle.
The stairs wind up in very sharp curves.
And all of these curves are right hand curves all of them.
So you're climbing up the stairs, you have to take a right turn, and then another right turn, and then the right turn.
Do you know why?
Just like a quiz, question.
Because you have no protection in your right side.
That was some kind of genius Muslim architecture that even if somebody breaks in.
They could be attacked very easily because you have protections from the left.
So in every turn, they could be ambushed.
So, when Khalid(خالد) was laying siege to a town one of their fighters came out of the gates with a sword in his right hand
and a shield in his left, and he asked for a duel.
So a Muslim volunteered to fight him and he killed him.
Then the Muslim asked for a duel.
So they sent out to him the greatest fighter, the Muslim then killed him.
He asked for a third duel.
This time they told him, let the devil fight you.
Go and fight with Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ)!
Ali(علي) said. Ut'ba Bin Rabiyah(عُتْبَة بن ربيعة), his son Al-Walid(ألوليد),
and his brother Shaibah(شيبة) came out in Badr(بدر) asking for duels,
three young men from Ansaar(ألأنْصَار) went to face them Ut'ba(عُتْبَة), ask them who they were?
When they introduced themselves, he said:
We have no desire in fighting you, send out to us, our equals from our own people.
Now, in a duel, the objective is not just to kill anyone.
The objective is that you want to kill somebody who's on the same level as you.
So number one, these were young.
Number two, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), didn't have a quarrel with Ansaar(ألأنْصَار).
Their problem was with Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون) from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So Ut'ba(عُتْبَة) wanted to fight people from his own people, send out to me, people equivalent to us.
Now Ut'ba(عُتْبَة), was from the nobility of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And he was one of their most prominent leaders.
So when that happened, Rasool Allah ﷺ, decided to send out his own relatives to go and fight.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said, stand up Hamza(حمزه)! Stand up Ali(علي)! Stand up Ubaidah Bin Haris(عبيدة بن حارث),
Al-Haris(ألحارث), is the uncle of Rasool Allah ﷺ, so Obaidah(عبيدة) is the cousin of Rasool Ullah.
Al-Haris(ألحارث) is the eldest son of Abdul Mutalib(عبدالمطلب).
Hamza(حمزه) faced Ut'ba(عُتْبَة), and killed him.
And I faced Shaibah(شيبة) and killed him.
While Obaidah(عبيدة) and Al-Walid(ألوليد), both injured each other and fell down.
Hamza(حمزه) and myself, walked up to Al-Walid(ألوليد) and killed him.
We then carried Obaidah(عبيدة) away, Obaidah(عبيدة) ended up dying shortly after that.
So this was the first Mubariza(مُبَارزَة) of Muslims
and that's why Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) says, about the Ayah(آية),
هٰذانِ خَصمانِ اختَصَموا في رَبِّهِم ۖ
فَالَّذينَ كَفَروا قُطِّعَت لَهُم ثِيابٌ مِن نارٍ يُصَبُّ مِن فَوقِ رُءوسِهِمُ الحَميمُ۞
The Ayah(آية) that says on the Day of Judgment, two men will come and dispute,
the issue of who was following Allah,
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said this Ayah(آية) is talking about me,
when we fought on that Mubariza(مُبَارزَة),
because this was the first fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) in terms of one on one,
even though there were some skirmishes before, but in terms of an army facing an army.
This was the first time.
CHAPTER 10
The severe punishment for the one, who turns his back during battle.
Allah says:
يا أَيُّهَا الَّذينَ آمَنوا إِذا لَقيتُمُ الَّذينَ كَفَروا زَحفًا فَلا تُوَلّوهُمُ الأَدبارَ۞
وَمَن يُوَلِّهِم يَومَئِذٍ دُبُرَهُ إِلّا مُتَحَرِّفًا لِقِتالٍ أَو مُتَحَيِّزًا
أَو مُتَحَيِّزًا إِلىٰ فِئَةٍ فَقَد باءَ بِغَضَبٍ مِنَ اللَّهِ
وَمَأواهُ جَهَنَّمُ ۖ وَبِئسَ المَصيرُ۞
O you have believed, when you meet those who disbelieve advancing for battle, do not turn to them your back.
يا أَيُّهَا الَّذينَ آمَنوا إِذا لَقيتُمُ الَّذينَ كَفَروا زَحفًا فَلا تُوَلّوهُمُ الأَدبارَ۞
وَمَن يُوَلِّهِم يَومَئِذٍ دُبُرَهُ إِلّا مُتَحَرِّفًا لِقِتالٍ أَو مُتَحَيِّزًا إِلىٰ فِئَةٍ فَقَد باءَ بِغَضَبٍ مِنَ اللَّهِ وَمَأواهُ جَهَنَّمُ ۖ وَبِئسَ المَصيرُ۞
And whoever turns his back to them on Such a day,
unless swerving as a strategy for war, or joining another company,
has certainly returned with anger from Allah and his refuge is hell, and retched is the destination.
And that's Al-Anfal(ألأنفال) Verse 15 and 16.
Realize that turning ones back in battle, is a major sin according to the consensus of the scholars
and the one, who does it deserve the Wrath of Allah and His severe punishment.
Abu Hurairah(أبوهريرة) narrated the Messenger of Allah said:
Stay away from the seven destroyers of your deeds,
Associating another deity with Allah, Shirk(شرك),
Sorcery, Sihr(سحر),
Murder. Al-Qatl(ألقتل),
asserping the wealth of an orphan,
عكرمال اليتيم
dealing with interest, Riba(رباء),
turning one's back during battle,
and accusing the chaste with adultery and fornication.
And by the way with this last one,
the Muslims knows the Hukm(حكم) of Zina(زنا),
they know the outcome of drinking alcohol,
they know the outcome of murder,
but many times people don't know the Hukum(حكم) of accusing a chaste woman or man with Zina(زنا).
And talking about these issues without having evidence.
This is one of the areas, and this is a very dangerous crime because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ said:
وَالَّذينَ يَرمونَ المُحصَناتِ ثُمَّ لَم يَأتوا بِأَربَعَةِ شُهَداءَ فَاجلِدوهُم ثَمانينَ جَلدَةً
فَاجلِدوهُم ثَمانينَ جَلدَةً وَلا تَقبَلوا لَهُم شَهادَةً أَبَدًا ۚ
وَأُولٰئِكَ هُمُ الفاسِقونَ۞
That they should be lash 80 times, and Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ said that their Shahadah(شَهَادَة) should never be accepted,
and they are fasiq(فاسق).
So it's very, very dangerous thing one should never ever accuse, and especially when it comes to women.
One should never ever accused, a woman of such a crime without the evidence
and the only evidence acceptable in Islam is four witnesses.
And this Hadith(حديث) is in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(ألمسلم).
If Jihad(جهاد) collective duty it becomes an individual duty, when the armies meet
and turning one's back becomes prohibited the only exceptions are!
We talked about the three conditions when Jihad(جهاد) becomes farz Aain(فرض عين), right!
You remember them, what are they?
Number one. When two armies meet, even if it was a Farz Kifaya(فرض كفاية) battle,
but when the armies meet, it becomes Farz Aain(فرض عين).
Second, Istafaar Al-Ameer(إستفارالأمير).
And number three, when the enemy invades your land.
The only exceptions are,
the size of the enemy's army is more than twice that of the Muslims.
Number two, swerving to take a new position.
Number three, retreating to join another company of Muslims.
Number four, being incapacitated, due to illness or having no access to a weapon.
An-Nawwawi(ألنووِي) quotes Ar-Rafae(ألرفاعي)'s saying:
If the enemy is more than double the size of the Muslims army,
then if the Muslims think that if they would remain steadfast, they can win, then they should remain steadfast.
But if they think that most likely they would perish, then it is allowed for them to retreat,
but it's better for them to fight, even if they think they would be killed.
Now this issue apparently there's difference of opinion on.
Because An-Nawwawi(ألنووِي) comments and he says that
retreat in this situation is not mandatory but it's recommended.
So for An-Nawwawi(ألنووِي), it's recommended to retreat,
if you think that you would perish.
The Mazhab(مذهب) of Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ), is that if the enemy's army is twice the size of the Muslims
and the Muslims think that most likely they would perish, if they fight,
and would be safe if they retreat,
then it's better for them to retreat but it's also allowed for them to fight and seek martyrdom.
So you see the difference of opinion.
The view of Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس),
the stronger opinion is that if a Muslim remains steadfast in a place that does not hurt the enemy,
and only leads to his own demise, it is a sin to do so.
An example would be a blind man fighting an enemy without any arms.
But if the Muslims, stay and fight with courage, and with the intention of seeking martyrdom,
and you can harm the enemy and he is killed, he would be rewarded by Allah.
Now, keep in mind, brothers that in applying this Hukum(حكم) on today's circumstances,
one needs to be very careful because the methods of battle today are very different.
This new method of guerrilla warfare has greatly affected the rules of battle,
so in guerrilla warfare really numbers is not that much of an issue anymore.
So when applying these rules, maybe this issue needs to be studied further on modern forms of warfare,
because in a guerrilla warfare if you have 300, 400 soldiers they can basically take on a huge army,
because it is not an actually, an army facing one another on an open plain field,
but it's Qarr Wal Farr(كرَّوالفر) method of attacking and retreating, attacking and retreating.
So when we were talking about this Fiqh(فقه) of numbers here,
I think, it cannot be applied straightforward as it is, in Fiqh(فقه) to the situations of today,
and some other elements need to be looked at.
Therefore, one needs to look at the Maqasid(مقاصد) of this Fiqh(فقه), rather than the, the numbers themselves.
So, we can notice from the words of the scholars that,
it is only when you fear that you would be exterminated, then you should retreat.
So that should be the guiding element.
If an army feels that they would be exterminated then, they should not involve in a particular fight,
whether the number is one to 10 or five to 10, or
if they feel that they have a chance to make it and fight to survive, then they should not retreat.
Allah says,
يا أَيُّهَا النَّبِيُّ حَرِّضِ المُؤمِنينَ عَلَى القِتالِ ۚ
إِن يَكُن مِنكُم عِشرونَ صابِرونَ يَغلِبوا مِائَتَينِ ۚ
وَإِن يَكُن مِنكُم مِائَةٌ يَغلِبوا أَلفًا مِنَ الَّذينَ كَفَروا
مِنَ الَّذينَ كَفَروا بِأَنَّهُم قَومٌ لا يَفقَهونَ۞
الآنَ خَفَّفَ اللَّهُ عَنكُم وَعَلِمَ أَنَّ فيكُم ضَعفًا ۚ
فَإِن يَكُن مِنكُم مِائَةٌ صابِرَةٌ يَغلِبوا مِائَتَينِ ۚ
وَإِن يَكُن مِنكُم أَلفٌ يَغلِبوا أَلفَينِ بِإِذنِ اللَّهِ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ مَعَ الصّابِرينَ۞
If there are among you 20 steadfast, they would overcome 200.
And if they are among 100 steadfast, they would overcome 1000 of those who have disbelieved,
because they are a people who do not understand.
Now Allah has lightened the hardship for you, and He knows that among you is weakness.
So if there are from you 100 steadfast, they will overcome 200.
And if there are among you 1000, they will overcome 2000 by the permission of Allah.
And Allah is with the steadfast, this is Al-Anfal(الأنفال) verse 65, 66.
إِن يَكُن مِنكُم عِشرونَ صابِرونَ يَغلِبوا مِائَتَينِ ۚ
وَإِن يَكُن مِنكُم مِائَةٌ يَغلِبوا أَلفًا مِنَ الَّذينَ كَفَروا بِأَنَّهُم قَومٌ لا يَفقَهونَ۞
الآنَ خَفَّفَ اللَّهُ عَنكُم وَعَلِمَ أَنَّ فيكُم ضَعفًا ۚ فَإِن يَكُن مِنكُم مِائَةٌ صابِرَةٌ يَغلِبوا مِائَتَينِ ۚ
وَإِن يَكُن مِنكُم أَلفٌ يَغلِبوا أَلفَينِ بِإِذنِ اللَّهِ ۗ وَاللَّهُ مَعَ الصّابِرينَ۞
Ibn Mubarak(إبن المبارك) narrated that in Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) said,
if one man retreats from three, he hasn't turned his back in battle.
If he retreats from two than he has turned his back in battle.
So that's the determinant factor in terms of numbers.
Al-Qurtubi(ألقرطبي) in his Tafseer(تفسير), he said:
As long as the enemy is more than twice the number of Muslims,
And you'll notice here, Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) quoting Al-Qurtubi(ألقرطبي) a lot.
And again I said that, when it comes to the fuqaha(فقهاء) you would find that
the Fiqh(فقه) of Jihad(جهاد) among the scholars of Andalus(أندلس) is a bit more lively,
because it was something that they lived.
I mean that was the land of Jihad(جهاد) and Ribat(رباط),
unlike, for example, when you look at the Tafseer(تفسير) of Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر),
you don't find a lot of details like you would find with Al-Qurtubi(ألقرطبي).
Because the experiences of a scholar do affect the way they look at things.
Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه) for example because he himself was involved in Jihad(جهاد),
one of the most important references when it comes to Jihad(جهاد) is the volume of his Fatawa(فتاوى),
an entire volume which was on Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
As long as the enemy is more than twice the number of Muslims,
by the way when I am mentioning the Mujallad(مجلد) of Jihad(جهاد), by Ibn Taymiyah(اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه),
I would say that the brothers who are interested in the Fiqh(فقه) of Jihad(جهاد) should go back to that reference.
It is one of the excellent references on the Fiqh(فقه) of Jihad(جهاد).
It should be part of your library if this, if the aspect of Fiqh(فقه) interests you.
If you're looking at the Fazail(فضائل), there's nothing that beats Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس).
Even though Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) does talk about Fiqh(فقه),
but it's, not as elaborate and detailed as Fatawa Ibn Taymiyah(فتاوى اِبْنِ تَيْمِيَّه).
As long as the enemy is more than twice the number of Muslims they can retreat,
but being steadfast and fighting is better.
The Battle of Mu'tah(مَؤتَة) and Muslims were only 3000,
and they faced the Roman army of 200,000, Roman soldiers and 100,000 Arab soldiers.
It was also, it is also mentioned that when Tariq(طارق) opened Andlusiya(أندلوسيه) he only had 1700 soldiers.
Other references say 7000,
while his enemy was 70,000 strong.
Imam Malik(إمام مالك) was asked about the Muslim facing 10 enemy soldiers should you fight them, or retreat,
he said: Both options are allowed for him.
Tayeb(طيب),
There's a hadith of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
ولا يُغْلَبُ اثنا عشرَ ألفًا من قِلَّةٍ
An army of 12,000 would never be defeated due to fewness,
and this is Narrated by Abu Daud(أبوداؤد), Al Sunnan Al-Kubra(ألسنن ألكبرى), At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ), Ad-Darimi(ألدارمي), Al-Hakim(ألحَاكِم).
So Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) says:
Most of the scholars consider this Hadith(حديث) to be an exception from the rule set by the verse
that as long as the enemy is more than twice your number, you can retreat.
The scholars say that this rule applies to armies less than 12,000 in numbers.
However, if the Muslim army has 12,000 or more, they cannot turn their back no matter how large the enemy is.
If the Muslims reach the number of 12,000, good trained fighters,
then no matter what the size of the enemy army is, they should not retreat.
Due to the Hadith(حديث).
ولا يُغْلَبُ اثنا عشرَ ألفًا من قِلَّةٍ
So the Hadith(حديث) says: They will not be defeated, due to fewness.
If they're defeated it would be because of another reason,
either disobedience of the Ameer(أمير), sins, disunity, but it's not due to lack of numbers,
even if they're facing a million.
So the Hadith(حديث) does not guarantee that they would win,
the Hadith(حديث) is guarantying that they will not lose due to numbers.
Did you get the meaning of the Hadith(حديث).?
The next few pages are not in your notes, unfortunately,
these were few pages that somehow apparently I forgot to translate.
It is a section on Allah is with the Mujahideen(مجاهدين).
We can provide you with the notes later on In Sha Allah(إنْ شاءالله).
Allah is with His creation in two forms,
Number one, Maeyyah Aamah(معية عامة),
Allah is with all of His creation, in terms of His knowledge and His Qudra(قدرة).
The knowledge of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and the Qudra(قدرة) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ encompasses all of the Creation.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
هُوَ الَّذي خَلَقَ السَّماواتِ وَالأَرضَ في سِتَّةِ أَيّامٍ ثُمَّ استَوىٰ عَلَى العَرشِ ۚ
يَعلَمُ ما يَلِجُ فِي الأَرضِ وَما يَخرُجُ مِنها وَما يَنزِلُ مِنَ السَّماءِ وَما يَعرُجُ فيها ۖ وَهُوَ مَعَكُم أَينَ ما كُنتُم ۚ
وَاللَّهُ بِما تَعمَلونَ بَصيرٌ۞
He it is, Who created the heavens and the earth in six days,
and is more ever firmly established on the throne.
He knows what enters within the earth and what comes forth out of it.
What comes down from the heaven and what mounts up to it,
and He is with you, wherever you may be, and Allah sees well, all that you do.
And this is Al-Hadid(ألحديد) verse Four.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: In Surat Mujadla(سورة المجادلة) verse 7.
أَلَم تَرَ أَنَّ اللَّهَ يَعلَمُ ما فِي السَّماواتِ وَما فِي الأَرضِ ۖ
ما يَكونُ مِن نَجوىٰ ثَلاثَةٍ إِلّا هُوَ رابِعُهُم وَلا خَمسَةٍ إِلّا هُوَ سادِسُهُم
وَلا أَدنىٰ مِن ذٰلِكَ وَلا أَكثَرَ إِلّا هُوَ مَعَهُم أَينَ ما كانوا ۖ
ثُمَّ يُنَبِّئُهُم بِما عَمِلوا يَومَ القِيامَةِ ۚ إِنَّ اللَّهَ بِكُلِّ شَيءٍ عَليمٌ۞
See you not that Allah does know all that is in the heavens and on earth.
There is not a secret consultation between the three, but Allah is their fourth,
nor between five, but Allah is there six nor between fewer nor more but He is with them, wherever they may be.
And in the end, will He tell them the truth of their conduct.
On the day of judgment for Allah has full knowledge of all things.
So this is general, presence of Allah.
But then there's a special Presence of Allah and that says his presence with Al-Mujahideen(ألمجاهدين).
This is a special presence with the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) and with the Saliheen(صالحين).
For example, in the Jihad(جهاد) of Musa(موسى) with Firaun(فرعون).
When Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ told Musa(موسى) and Harun(هارون), to go to the court of Firaun(فرعون).
And you know, this is the one situation that,
I don't really think that we will appreciate what Musa(موسى) and Harun(هارون) were going through
because we have not lived those circumstances.
Musa عليه السّلام left Egypt because he was wanted dead are alive.
They wanted to execute him because he killed an Egyptian.
He left Egypt for 10 years, left his family left his country.
Right!
And he's fugitive.
And now Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ is not telling him just to sneak into Egypt,
Allah is telling you to go publicly and goes straight to Firaun(فرعون) and to tell Firaun(فرعون), I want you to follow me.
How can you pull that together.
So for Musa(موسى) it was a different difficult command.
And he said: He and Haroon(هارون) they said:
قالا رَبَّنا إِنَّنا نَخافُ أَن يَفرُطَ عَلَينا أَو أَن يَطغىٰ۞
O Allah, We are afraid that we might be killed.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ told them:
قالَ لا تَخافا ۖ إِنَّني مَعَكُما أَسمَعُ وَأَرىٰ۞
Don't be afraid, I am with you. I see, and I hear.
Don't be worry, I'm with you.
So this is a special presence of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says,
فَلا تَهِنوا وَتَدعوا إِلَى السَّلمِ وَأَنتُمُ الأَعلَونَ وَاللَّهُ مَعَكُم وَلَن يَتِرَكُم أَعمالَكُم۞
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: So be not weak and ask not for peace,
while you are having the upper hand, Allah is with you.
Why are you asking for peace, when Allah is with you.?
Why are you giving in what Allah is with you, you don't really need anybody else.?
And He will never decrease the reward of your good deeds.
Or when Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) in the cave.
إِذ يَقولُ لِصاحِبِهِ لا تَحزَن إِنَّ اللَّهَ مَعَنا ۖ
He is telling to his companion: Don't be saddened, Allah is with us!
Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) says whenever the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) faults on a certain aspect of his worship or commit sins,
he becomes similar to the enemy in that aspect.
And that would lead to darkness entering his heart.
So, when you commit a sin, you become similar to the enemy, in that particular area,
according to how many sins are committed.
That is how similar, you become with the enemy.
It could lead to him suffering from some fear and weakness,
and thus would become more attached to this life
and the effects of these sins of the Mujahid(مُجَاهِد) is proportionate to the magnitude of the sin.
Don't you see what happened during the Battle of Hunain(حنين), when one of the Muslims said:
We are not going to be defeated because of our numbers, one of the Muslims said:
لن نغلب اليوم أن قلة
Because the Muslims were 12,000, the Muslims never amassed such a huge army.
10,000, who came to Fath-e-Makkah(فتح مكة), two Thousand from Muslim At-Fath(مسلم الفتح),
the ones who became Muslim in Makkah, 12,000.
So the Muslims, saw this and they were very impressed.
He said: We cannot lose this battle, 12000 strong.
That was a sin! Why was it a sin, because those are the criteria of the Kuffar(كفار).
It is the Kuffar(كفار), who look at numbers, who look at equipment,
but the Muslim looks at the assistance of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
For the Muslims victory comes from Allah, it doesn't come from numbers or equipments.
لَقَد نَصَرَكُمُ اللَّهُ في مَواطِنَ كَثيرَةٍ ۙ وَيَومَ حُنَينٍ ۙ
وَيَومَ حُنَينٍ ۙ إِذ أَعجَبَتكُم كَثرَتُكُم فَلَم تُغنِ عَنكُم شَيئًا
وَضاقَت عَلَيكُمُ الأَرضُ بِما رَحُبَت ثُمَّ وَلَّيتُم مُدبِرينَ۞
وَيَومَ حُنَينٍ ۙ إِذ أَعجَبَتكُم كَثرَتُكُم
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: On the day of Hunain(حنين), you're impressed with your numbers,
فَلَم تُغنِ عَنكُم شَيئًا
They did you no good! They did you no good!
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
Don't you see what happened during the battle, assuredly Allah did help you in many battlefields.
And on the day of Hunain(حنين) behold your great numbers, elated you,
but they availed you not.
And Allah said about in Uhud(أحَد).
إِنَّ الَّذينَ تَوَلَّوا مِنكُم يَومَ التَقَى الجَمعانِ إِنَّمَا استَزَلَّهُمُ الشَّيطانُ بِبَعضِ ما كَسَبوا ۖ
وَلَقَد عَفَا اللَّهُ عَنهُم ۗ إِنَّ اللَّهَ غَفورٌ حَليمٌ۞
Those of you, who turn back on the day the two hosts met, it was Satan who caused them to fail
because of some evil they had done, but Allah has blotted out their fault.
For Allah is oft forgiving, most Forbearing,
and this is Al-Imran(ألعمران) Verse 155.
In the Battle of Uhud(أحَد), the defeat on that day was, because of,
what was the reason?
Disobeying Rasool Allah ﷺ.
There was a small hill, Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed 50 archers to take that post.
And then you have maybe one kilometer distance
and then you have the mountain Uhud(أحَد), which is about eight kilometers long.
So, the Muslims had their front facing the enemy,
but then their flank was to this small hill.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ felt that the Muslims could be attacked from behind.
So he appointed these 50 archers to protect them.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told these archers.
If you see us winning, Do not come down, if you see us losing, do not come down,
even if you see vultures, eating our dead bodies.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying: I don't want you to help me, in the fighting, I just wanted to stay there and protect our backs.
That's it.!
And brothers, this illustrates the importance of following the order,
and when the order is specific don't make a judgment on your own.
Rasool Allah ﷺ gave them a specific order, even if you see us dying don't come down,
and if you see us winning do not come down, he made it very clear.
The Muslims won.
The enemies were on the run,
and one of the Sahabah(صحابه) said: We could see the khalakhal(خلاخل) of their women.
khalakhal(خلاخل) are the bracelets they have on their feet.
We could see them running.
Now, the Muslims, got involved in collecting the booty of war
and these 50 men on top of the mountain, they thought it's all over.
And they started getting a bit itchy
and they were telling the Ameer(أمير), let us go and pick up some of these spoils of war.
Abdullah Bin Jubair(عبدالله بن جبير) said: We have clear commands from Rasool Allah ﷺ to stay here.
40 of them disobey the Ameer(أمير) and went down, 40.
So only 10 remained on the mountain.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), this was his first experience in leading a cavalry in war.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), he detected with his eagle eyes that there's a weak point, there's a weak spot.
So he made his move, alongside Iqrima Bin Abi Jahal(عكرمة بن أبي جهل),
and they went around the mountain of Uhud(أحَد), according to one opinion, it's around the hill,
but the other opinion which seems to be stronger if you see the battlefield,
is that they went behind the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
And a fast horse can make that distance in a few minutes,
it's about eight kilometers long but fast horses can make it.
So they went all the way behind the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
And they attacked the Muslims from behind and they just cut through them.
And that is when 70 of the Muslims were killed.
It was a massacre among the Muslims, seventy of them got killed.
Why did this all happen because of disobeying the commands Of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
They made the judgment on their own, they said the battle is over.
So, they lost in Hunain(حنين) because of sin, they lost in Uhud(أحَد) because of sin.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
يا أَيُّهَا الَّذينَ آمَنوا قاتِلُوا الَّذينَ يَلونَكُم مِنَ الكُفّارِ وَليَجِدوا فيكُم غِلظَةً ۚ
وَاعلَموا أَنَّ اللَّهَ مَعَ المُتَّقينَ۞
Oh you, who believe, fight the unbelievers who gird you about,
and let them find firmness in you, and know that Allah is with those who, fear Him.
So Allah is with those who fear Him.
And Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) says: And Rasool Allah ﷺ was eager to teach his Ummah(امة), the Presence of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ) narrates that Ibn Abbas رضي الله عنه said:
And this Hadith(حديث) is a famous Hadith(حديث), if you must have heard it.
عن إبنِ عَبْاسٍ رَضي اللهُ عنه قال:بينما كُنْتُ رديفًا النَّبِيِّ صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ قال
"يا غُلامُ، إنِّي أُعَلِّمُكَ كلِماتٍ: احْفَظِ اللهَ يَحْفَظك، احْفَظِ اللهَ تَجِدْهُ تُجاهَك،
إذا سأَلْتَ فاسْأَلِ اللهَ، وإذا اسْتَعنْتَ فاسْتَعِنْ باللهِ،
واعْلَمْ أنَّ الأُمَّة لَو اجْتَمَعَتْ على أَنْ يَنْفَعُـوكَ بِشَيءٍ
لَمْ يَنْفَعُوكَ إلا بِشَيْءٍ قدْ كَتَبَهُ اللهُ لَكَ،
ولو اجْتَمَعُوا على أن يَضُرَّوكَ بِشيءٍ لَمْ يَضُروكَ إلا بِشَيء قد كَتَبهُ اللهُ عَلَيْكَ،
رُفِعَتِ الأقْلامُ وَجَفَّتِ الصُّحُفُ
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) says: And this Hadith(حديث) is in At-Tirmidhi(ألتِّرمِذِيْ)
that I was riding with Rasool Allah ﷺ behind him,
so he told me: O young man, I will teach you a few words.
Be mindful of Allah, Allah will be mindful of you!
Be mindful of Allah, Allah will be with you!
If you ask then ask Allah, and if you seek refuge, then seek refuge in Allah
and realize that if the entire creation, the whole Ummah(امة) come together to benefit you with something,
they would not benefit you except with something that was destined for you.
And if they all come together to harm you,
they won't harm you except with something that was destined to happen against you,
the pens are lifted and the scrolls are dry.
Be mindful of Allah, Allah, Allah will be mindful of you.
Be mindful of Allah, Allah will be with you.
This manifests itself in a few ways.
First of all, what does it mean,
احْفَظِ اللهَ
Be mindful of Allah.
The scholars say, and
تجتنب نواحي وتفعل عوابر
You stay away from what Allah made Haram(حرام), and you do what Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ commanded you to do.
If you do that it's a cause and it's reflecting,
if you do that, then the result, the consequence of that would be,
Allah will be mindful of you and Allah will be with you,
and how will that happen.?
One way is if you take care of your body when you're young, Allah will take care of it when you're old.
One scholar and he was about 100 years of age, and he made this long leap.
So his students told him: Take it easy, you might fall down and break a bone or something.
He said:
هذه جوار حفظناها في السلم فحفظه الله لنا من كبر
He said: I use these limbs to take care of the commands of Allah when I'm young,
so Allah will take care of them when I'm old,
that's number one.
Number two,
You take care of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, Allah will take care of your children
and this is very, very important especially for Muslims living in the West.
We are always wondering how, what will happen to my kids in this environment.
If you take care of the commands of Allah, Allah will take care of your children.
And what's the evidence for that.?
There's an evidence in Qur'an: What is it?
Surah Al-Kahf(سورة الكهف),
Which Ayah(آية) is it.?
What is that Ayah(آية) talking about?
Okay, when Musa(موسى) and Al-Khadhar(خضر) went into this town.
The Haqq(حَقّ) of Ziyafah(ظيلفة) is that you're hosted for three days.
Right!
This is, you know, this is not something voluntary, I mean the scholars says it's mandatory.
So the three days is, a duty that you have towards the Muslims.
So, they went into this town, and they asked for them to host them for three days.
And the people in this town refused.
Now, Al-Khadhar(ألخضر) sees this wall that is about to fall down.
And he rebuilds it, and he does it, for free.
Musa(موسى) wasn't happy, these people were so stingy, they didn't host us,
and you build this wall for free, and then Musa(موسى) saw some contradiction in this.
Because in the beginning of the story when they went on this boat.
Right!
The owners of the boat delivered them for free.
And what does Al-Khadhar(ألخضر) do.?
He breaks a panel off the boat.
So these people who deliver us for free do us a favor you break a panel from their boat.
And then here you have these stingy people, you do them, you build this wall for free and it's contradicting.
So Musa(موسى) opposed what Al-Khadhar(ألخضر) was doing.
So Al-Khadhar(ألخضر) said: That's the end of it, that's the end of it.
Our relationship is over,
and I'm going to tell you why I did what I did.?
The reason why I rebuilt this wall is because under the wall was a treasure,
and it belonged two orphans, and I wanted them to grow up to be able to retrieve their treasure,
because you know if these village people are so stingy.
If this treasure shows up, what will they do with it.
Will they give it to these two young kids?
They're going to take it, they're not going to give them anything.
So Al-Khadhar(ألخضر) wants to build it, so that when these two boys grow up, they can retrieve it and fight for it.
But why Al-Khadhar(ألخضر) gave a justification for it.
He said:
وَكانَ أَبوهُما صالِحًا
The reason why I rebuild the wall is because their father was righteous.
Now, because of the righteousness of the father,
Allah took care of the children not when the father was traveling somewhere or is out of home, when he was dead.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will not take only take care of your children when you're alive
or when you're traveling or when you're not at home.
Allah will take care of them even after you pass away.
And you know especially for somebody who is going Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
this is a constant thought on their mind what will my family do.
Realize that if you have a Taqwa(تقوى) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will take care of your family
because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ sent Al-Khadhar(ألخضر) all the way to rebuild this wall,
just to take care of those two orphans whom, their father passed away.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ took care of them because of the righteousness of the Father.
So if you take care of the commands of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and there's any good in your family.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will take care of them.
And if there's no good in them, in your presence or in your absence, it's not going to make a difference.
You know, Umar Ibn Abdel Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز) when he was passing away, we told we talked about his story.
Did we talk about what happened with his children.
He said,
إمَّا صالح او فاجر
My son is either gonna grow up to be righteous, or to be corrupt.
If my son is righteous, then Allah will give them Rizq(رزق) because of their righteousness,
and if my son is corrupt, then I don't want to support them on their corruption.
I don't want to be part of that I'm not gonna leave anything behind.
For them to use it for evil.
So take care of the commands of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will take care of your family.
Obviously that doesn't mean neglecting them,
see neglect is something,
and doing what needs to be done is something else.
Sometimes, you end up neglecting the family because of more of a priority of duties that you have towards Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
This is when Allah will, take care of them,
but when we have nothing to do, and you're still neglecting the family, then.
That's a different situation.
So that's one way Allah will take care of you.
A third way you take care of the commands of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ,
Allah will take care of you in two of the most difficult situations you could run through in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا),
most dangerous situations on you Deen(دِيْن).
And that is Ash-Shahwat(ألشهوات) and Ash-Shubuhat(شبهات).
Ash-Shubuhat(شبهات) are doubts,
Ash-Shahwat(ألشهوات) are desires.
You run into situations where Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) puts doubts in your heart,
these doubts can come in different forms either doubts in Allah, the existence of Allah,
doubts in the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, doubts in some parts of Shariah(شريعة),
doubts in Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Doubts could lead to anything.
And you wonder why, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has ordered us to do this.
Why did the Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ say that, or why did Rasool Allah ﷺ do this.?
These are very dangerous because they could take a person from Eeman(ايمان) to Kuffr(كفر).
And then you have Ash-Shahwat(ألشهوات), the desires,
lust, love of power and money.
If you take care of the commands of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and you are put in one of these two situations Allah will take care of you.
When Yusuf عليه السّلام was put in that extreme position of Fitnah(فِتْنَه),
a very handsome young man, unmarried and in front is a beautiful woman, who he owes a lot to,
because he was a servant for them, he was a slave owned by them.
And she has power and authority and wealth and she has all of the means to coerce him into Fitnah(فِتْنَه), Zina(زنا).
And he was put in this old situation that man could rarely,
or in fact we would say that maybe nobody could pass that situation,
except if Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gives them Burhan(برهان) which He gave to Yousaf عليه السّلام.
لولا أَن رَّأَى بُرْهَانَ رَبِّهِ
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ saved him through a Burhan(برهان), certain secret of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ which will give to him.
And it saved him in that position.
Why?
Because of the deeds that he used to do before.
Yunus عليه السّلام when he was stuck in that stomach of the whale,
he was in deep trouble.
Under the three layers of darkness,
what saved him.?
It is tasbiha(تسبح).
فَلَولا أَنَّهُ كانَ مِنَ المُسَبِّحينَ۞لَلَبِثَ في بَطنِهِ إِلىٰ يَومِ يُبعَثونَ۞
If it wasn't because he used to make the Tasbih(تسبيح) before,
he would have remained in the stomach of whale until the day of judgment.
Now, just a note to the parents, brothers over here who are fathers.
Notice that Rasool Allah ﷺ here is speaking to Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) who was less than 13 years of age at the time.
Because when Rasool Allah ﷺ passed away Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) was 13 years old.
So Allah Alam(ألله أعلم) he might be 13 or 12 or 11 or 10 when Rasool Ullah, telling this Hadith(حديث).
What is the Hadith(حديث) concentrating on.?
It is concentrating on Amaal Ul Qulub(أعمال القلوب), the deeds of the heart.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is planting these deeds of the heart in the heart of Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) at this early age,
and that's what, you want to convey it to your children.
Take care of Allah, Allah will take care of you.
Be mindful of Allah, Allah will be with you.
And then he's telling him ask ALLAH, seek refuge in Allah.
And then he's telling him that everything is Muqaddar(مقدر), everything is destined, whatever you do.
No one can harm you, except if that harm is destined by Allah,
and nobody can benefit you except if that was destined by Allah,
so don't worry about it.
These are very important meanings to deliver to our youngsters,
because it develops and then the strong Islamic personality,
otherwise they grew up to be weak, feeble, they might be praying and fasting, but their hearts are weak.
It could be a frail body, but it has a heart of a lion.
Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه was once climbing a palm tree.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) was very short and slim, very skinny.
So a wind gust hit Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود), when he was on top of the palm tree, so he was shaking.
And that uncovered his legs.
So the Sahabah(صحابه) saw these thin legs and they laughed, they laughed at his legs.
Look at those legs!
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
أَتَضْحَكُونَ مِنْ دِقَّةِ سَاقَيْهِ ؟
Are you laughing because of the thinness of his legs.
In the Name of Allah, on the Day of Judgment they are heavier on the scale than the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
Now brothers! This frail body and weak body of Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود),
that weak hand, or thin hand was the hand that cut off the head of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل),
the Firaun(فرعون) of this Ummah(امة).
It wasn't a big, muscular wrestler who killed the Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل).
It was Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود).
He is the one, after a Muawiz(معوذ) and Ma'az Bin Afrah(معاذ بن أفراح), who fought with Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل)
and the Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) was laying down and he wasn't dead yet, he was in his last moments.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود), he climbed over the chest of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل), when he was lying on his back,
he climbed over him, and he held the sword, and he wanted to cut off the head of Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل).
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) not only was he short and slim,
but he was also seen as being from a humble family in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He was a shepherd of goats.
So Abu Jahal(ابوجَهَل) told him,
لَقَدْ ارْتَقَيْتَ مُرْتَقًى صَعْبًا يَا رُوَيْعِي الْغَنَمِ
You're climbing a very high peak you shepherd of goats.
When he climbed on his chest, he said: You're climbing a very high peak, you shepherd of goats.
I mean it's not even appropriate for you to be sitting on my chest,
and that's when Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) cut off his head.
So it's not really the body, it is not the physical strength, it is the heart.
That's what you want to plant in the youth, Amal Qalb(أعمال ألقلب), strong hearts.
The early Mujahideen(مجاهدين) were very cautious from committing sins
because they knew the effect that had on their Jihad(جهاد).
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) mentions in his history book,
that one of the Muslims during the era of Sultan Az-Zahar Bin Bars(سلطان الزهر بن برص)
used to make Jihad(جهاد) on his horse, which was a strong and fast horse,
but one day his horse was acting very different, it was slow and disobedient,
so he was astonished by the reaction of his horse,
but then he realized the reason why, and remembered that he has fed his horse food purchased with a counterfeit coin.
So he could feel the resistance of the horse because of the Haram(حرام) food, that he gave it.
O Mujahid(مُجَاهِد), beware of disobeying Allah,
sins would weaken your heart and defeat your will,
purify your heart from contaminations and spark in, its darkness, the light of Tawakkul(توكل) and Yaqeen(يقين)
and have courage of the One, Who is certain, that death is inevitable and that nothing can protect you from it.
أَينَما تَكونوا يُدرِككُمُ المَوتُ وَلَو كُنتُم في بُروجٍ مُشَيَّدَةٍ ۗ
وَإِن تُصِبهُم حَسَنَةٌ يَقولوا هٰذِهِ مِن عِندِ اللَّهِ ۖ
وَإِن تُصِبهُم سَيِّئَةٌ يَقولوا هٰذِهِ مِن عِندِكَ ۚ
قُل كُلٌّ مِن عِندِ اللَّهِ ۖ
فَمالِ هٰؤُلاءِ القَومِ لا يَكادونَ يَفقَهونَ حَديثًا۞
أَينَما تَكونوا يُدرِككُمُ المَوتُ وَلَو كُنتُم في بُروجٍ مُشَيَّدَةٍ ۗ
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: Wherever you are, that will find you out.
Even if you are in towers, built up strong and high.
There's no way to get away from death.
And if Allah has destined for someone to be killed.
Nothing can change that faith.
Allah says,
ثُمَّ أَنزَلَ عَلَيكُم مِن بَعدِ الغَمِّ أَمَنَةً نُعاسًا يَغشىٰ طائِفَةً مِنكُم ۖ
وَطائِفَةٌ قَد أَهَمَّتهُم أَنفُسُهُم يَظُنّونَ بِاللَّهِ غَيرَ الحَقِّ ظَنَّ الجاهِلِيَّةِ ۖ
يَقولونَ هَل لَنا مِنَ الأَمرِ مِن شَيءٍ ۗ
قُل إِنَّ الأَمرَ كُلَّهُ لِلَّهِ ۗ
يُخفونَ في أَنفُسِهِم ما لا يُبدونَ لَكَ ۖ
يَقولونَ لَو كانَ لَنا مِنَ الأَمرِ شَيءٌ ما قُتِلنا هاهُنا ۗ
قُل لَو كُنتُم في بُيوتِكُم لَبَرَزَ الَّذينَ كُتِبَ عَلَيهِمُ القَتلُ إِلىٰ مَضاجِعِهِم ۖ
وَلِيَبتَلِيَ اللَّهُ ما في صُدورِكُم وَلِيُمَحِّصَ ما في قُلوبِكُم ۗ
وَاللَّهُ عَليمٌ بِذاتِ الصُّدورِ۞
يَقولونَ لَو كانَ لَنا مِنَ الأَمرِ شَيءٌ ما قُتِلنا هاهُنا ۗ
قُل لَو كُنتُم في بُيوتِكُم لَبَرَزَ الَّذينَ كُتِبَ عَلَيهِمُ القَتلُ إِلىٰ مَضاجِعِهِم ۖ
They say to themselves, if we had anything, if we had had anything to do with this affair,
we should not have been in this laughter here,
say, even if you had remained in your homes, those for whom death was decreed,
would certainly have gone forth to the place of their death.
That's Al-Imran(ألعمران) Verse 154.
There's a story of a man who fell down.
Apparently, it's told that story happened in Saudia(سعودية).
A man fell down from the seventh floor or something very high, landed on the pavement and he didn't die.
All of the reasons for dying were there and he didn't die.
So he was very amazed that he was actually alive so he stands up and he's so happy
and people gather around him, and he is just celebrating that Allah has given him a new life.
And he's telling to the people I'm gonna buy you some Pepsi(بيبسي), you know in Arabic you don't have a P.
I'm gonna get you some Bebsi(بيبسي).
So he crosses the street to go and buy them some Bebsi(بيبسي) and car rolls over him and he died.
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has made an appointment with him, with the angel of death in the middle of the road,
it wasn't on the pavement.
And Allah brought him down from the building, down to the pavement
and come to the exact place where he was destined to meet the angel of death.
That's where he died.
You cannot get away from it.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was looking for death, looking for it.
You know, and you can see it in his letters to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and in his statements.
In one of his letters to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he said:
And I have thrown myself in situations where I lost hope in living.
ولقد اكتحمت حتى أن يست من الحياة
Because in one of these battles.
He got married after the battle was over, he got married,
after the Battle of Yamamah(يمامة), he got married to the daughter Muja'ah(مجاعة)
one of the leaders from Banu Hanifa(بنوحنيفة), he got married to his daughter.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was very upset that he got married and he sends him a very harsh letter he says:
You're getting married and you're enjoying a women,
when you have in your court, the bodies of 700 Muslims,
I forgot the number who and their blood has not even dried yet.
How could you do that?
Because many Muslims died in the battle of Yamamah(يمامة).
So Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) sends a letter back he's saying:
I only got married after victory was complete.
And then he's telling Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق)
and I have thrown myself in situations in battle, where I have lost hope of living.
And then he told him:
And if my sadness, would revive the dead, they would have been revived.
But this is the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and nothing would change it.
In other words, it was the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allah that these die men die,
and if my love for them would make them live they would have lived.
Because they are so dear to me.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) when he is dying, he said,
there's not a single part of my body that was not struck by a sword, a spear, or an arrow,
and here I am dying on my bed.
So may the eyes of the cowards never get any sleep.
He is saying that I've thrown myself in all these situations one after another.
I have injuries all of all over my body and here I am dying on my bed.
لا يغني حاضرون عن قدر
Being cautious will not choose the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
O you who runs away from the battlefield,
Realize that running away will not extend your life and being steadfast wouldn't shorten it.
And remember that you have committed the grave sin, and you have clothed yourself with a cloak of humiliation.
Aren't you worried that you might be taken as a prisoner and tortured until you give up your religion,
so you end up losing this world and the last.
Aren't you afraid that you might be taken, and then eventually killed.
Whoever has any intelligence
would realize that facing death when it's time, has approached is better than turning your back towards it.
If your time of death is now, it's better for you to face it with your chest than to face it with your back.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says,
أقبلنًا غير مدبر
Facing Shahadah(شَهَادَة) not running away from it.
O you who runs away!
Aren't you concerned that while you are running away a stray arrow might strike you and kill you.
So you would end up being in hellfire.
The stories of those who lost their religion because they did not fight, and were taken as prisoners are many.
Al-Bayhaqi(ألبيهقي) narrates from Abdu Bin Abdur Rahim(عبدو بن عبدالرحيم).
This is an interesting story,
Abdu Bin Abdur Rahim(عبدو بن عبدالرحيم) narrates that we were in an army in the land of the Romans.
And we had with us, a young man.
Abdu Bin Abdur Rahim(عبدو بن عبدالرحيم) says: There was none among us who used to recite Qur'an better than him.
And he was the most knowledgeable among us, and he would spend his day fasting and his night praying.
He said: While we were passing next to one of the Roman fortresses,
he saw this Christian woman and he fell in love with her.
That's it!
From one side,
he was hooked to this woman, so he went to the fortress and he started speaking to her.
He said: How can I get access to you?
She said: Simple become Christian, and will open for you the gates.
He became Christian and they open the gates for him.
Abdu Bin Abdur Rahim(عبدو بن عبدالرحيم) said:
When we left, we were extremely disheartened and saddened by what happened.
He said: Then a long time passed, and we came back and we passed next to the same fortress.
And we saw this young man standing up on one of the observation posts,
along with Roman soldiers guarding the fortress.
So he went to him and said,
يا فلان ما فعل قرآن، ما فعلت بصلاتك وصيامك
Oh, so and so! What happened to your Qur'an, what's happened to your good deeds, what's happened to your fasting?
What's happened to your prayer.?
He said: In the name of Allah, I remember nothing from Qur'an except one verse.
And He recited to them the verse that he remembers.
He says:
رُبَما يَوَدُّ الَّذينَ كَفَروا لَو كانوا مُسلِمينَ۞
ذَرهُم يَأكُلوا وَيَتَمَتَّعوا وَيُلهِهِمُ الأَمَلُ ۖ فَسَوفَ يَعلَمونَ۞
He said: I remember nothing from Qur'an but one verse,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
Again and again, will those who disbelieve, wish that they had bowed in Islam.
Leave them alone to enjoy the good things of this life,
and to please themselves, let false hope amuse them,
soon will knowledge undeceive them,
look at the particular Ayah(آية) that he remembered.
رُبَما يَوَدُّ الَّذينَ كَفَروا لَو كانوا مُسلِمينَ۞
Maybe one day the disbelievers would desire that they would be believers.
Let them enjoy this life, the pleasures of this life and the false hope, because they will come to know the truth.
I give this story, so that you can only ask the Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to give you Thabat(ثبات).
However, when a Muslim fights sincerely, but then falls into captivity,
and his enemy tried to mislead him, Allah would protect him and be on his side.
An example would be the story of Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة), the companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Did we talked about his story.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة) was captured by the Romans.
The Romans were quite happy to have one of the Sahabah(صحابه),
you know for them was the Sahabah(صحابه) was a legendary figure.
Sahabah(صحابه), they would hear about them, all these strange legends, Sahabah(صحابه)!
So the Roman king, he wanted to meet this man,
so they brought him Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة).
He told him I want you to become Christian.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة) refused.
He said: If you don't, this is what will happen to you.
They had this huge pot with boiling water.
So they brought one of the Muslim prisoners of war and they threw him in the water.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة) said:
As soon as he landed in that water his flesh started just falling off the bones.
It's so hot, it just separates the flesh from the bones.
They said: If you don't become Christian, this is what we'll do.?
He said: I won't!
So they picked him up in order to throw him in the container.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة) started to cry.
So the king said: We got him, he has softened.
Now he is going to become Christian.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة) said: Don't think that the reason, why I cried, is because I feared death.
The reason why I cried, is because I realized that I only have one soul.
And I would have desire that Allah would give me souls, the number of hair that I have in my head,
so that I could give them one after another, in the path of Allah.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), you see somebody boil in front of you and you see his flesh separating from the bone
and then you wish that that happens to you, not once but 100 times,
a 100 times!!!
It's that I wish that I had as many souls as hair on my head,
to give them in Sabeel-Lillah(سَبيل الله) one after another.
The king was very impressed by that.
He said: Listen!
If you become Christian, I will marry you to my daughter and give you half of my kingdom,
half of my kingdom!!!
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة) said: No way!
Now the king wanted to get just anything from Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة).
He is trying everything and he's not getting anywhere.
He says: Alright! If you kiss my forehead, I'm gonna release you.
Just kiss my forehead!!!
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة) thought about that and he said:
Only if you're gonna release all of the Muslim prisoners of war with me.
The King said: I agree!
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة), he kisses him, and the king releases, all of the Muslim prisoners of war, all of them.
Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة) gets to Al-Madina,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) hears the news.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) stands up on the Mimber(ممبر) and says,
حقٌ على كل مسلم
It's a duty on every Muslim in Madina to go and kiss the forehead of Abdullah Bin Hudhafa(عبدالله بن حذافة).
So Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gave him Sabat(ثبات).
This was narrated by Ibn Al- Athir(اِبْنِ ألأثِيْر).
Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) says: It is not allowed for a Muslim to flee death.
If there was no virtue and martyrdom, other than being spared the agony of death,
that would have been sufficient enough to make a person refuse to retreat from the battlefield,
Saqrat-Ul-Moat(سكرات الموت).
Ali رضي الله عنه would encourage the Muslims to fight by saying:
If you are not killed, you would die.
In the Name of Allah 1000 strikes of a sword are less painful than dying on your bed.
Saqrat-Ul-Moat(سكرات الموت) are very painful.
The agony of death is very painful,
and Ali(علي) is saying that 1000 strikes of a sword are gonna hurt you less than dying on your bed.
Ibn Nuhas(إبن نُحاس) is saying this is sufficient enough to make you wanted as Shaheed(شَهِيد).
But then he says, in addition to that,
the one who dies on his bed will suffer from the agony of death and after that the darkness and the horror of the grave,
the questioning of the angels, the resurrection, the reckoning the weighing of deeds,
and the crossing of the bridge,
Shadad Bin Aus(شداد بن الأوس) would say death is the worst experience of this world, or the afterlife.
It is worse than being cut by saws or scissors or boiling water.
So which is better for you, dying in the path of Allah
or dying on your bed, you decide for yourself,
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says:
يا أَيُّهَا النّاسُ اتَّقوا رَبَّكُم ۚ إِنَّ زَلزَلَةَ السّاعَةِ شَيءٌ عَظيمٌ۞
يَومَ تَرَونَها تَذهَلُ كُلُّ مُرضِعَةٍ عَمّا أَرضَعَت وَتَضَعُ كُلُّ ذاتِ حَملٍ حَملَها
وَتَضَعُ كُلُّ ذاتِ حَملٍ حَملَها وَتَرَى النّاسَ سُكارىٰ وَما هُم بِسُكارىٰ
وَما هُم بِسُكارىٰ وَلٰكِنَّ عَذابَ اللَّهِ شَديدٌ۞
يا أَيُّهَا النّاسُ اتَّقوا رَبَّكُم ۚ إِنَّ زَلزَلَةَ السّاعَةِ شَيءٌ عَظيمٌ۞
O mankind Fear your Lord!
For the convulsion of the Hour of judgment will be a terrible thing.
يَومَ تَرَونَها تَذهَلُ كُلُّ مُرضِعَةٍ عَمّا أَرضَعَت وَتَضَعُ كُلُّ ذاتِ حَملٍ حَملَها
وَتَرَى النّاسَ سُكارىٰ وَما هُم بِسُكارىٰ وَلٰكِنَّ عَذابَ اللَّهِ شَديدٌ۞
The day you shall see it.
Every mother giving suck shall forget her suckling baby,
and every pregnant female she'll drop her load, thou shall see mankind as in a drunken riot,
yet not drunk, but dreadful would be the Wrath of Allah,
and then compare this to what the Allah says about the Shuhadaa(شُهَدآء).
وَلا تَحسَبَنَّ الَّذينَ قُتِلوا في سَبيلِ اللَّهِ أَمواتًا ۚ
بَل أَحياءٌ عِندَ رَبِّهِم يُرزَقونَ۞
فَرِحينَ بِما آتاهُمُ اللَّهُ مِن فَضلِهِ
وَيَستَبشِرونَ بِالَّذينَ لَم يَلحَقوا بِهِم مِن خَلفِهِم أَلّا خَوفٌ عَلَيهِم وَلا هُم يَحزَنونَ۞
Think not of those who are slain in the Allah’s way and dead,
Nay they live, finding their sustenance in the presence of their Lord.
They rejoice in the bounty provided by Allah
and with regard to those left behind, who have not yet joined them in their bliss.
The martyrs glory in the fact that on them has no fear, nor have they cause to grief,
and this is Al-Imran(ألعمران) Verse 169 and 170.
These martyrs are saved from the greatest fears and their abode is paradise.
Their souls are in the insides of green birds.
I guess some of you are tired so might need to take a break.